Guide to the Dick Hedges World War II Memorabilia Collection, MS 422, 1944-46 MS 422
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Dick Hedges World War II Memorabilia Collection
1944-46
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Hedges, Dixon D. (Dick)
MS 422
4.25 Linear Feet
This collection consists of books, magazines, newspapers, clippings, photographs, photograph albums, maps, town plans, reports, writings and memorabilia, which were collected by Dick Hedges while he was serving with the U. S. Army in Europe in World War II.
Biographical / Historical
Dick Hedges was drafted into the United States Army in December of 1942. He was sent first to Dodd Field (Fort Sam Houston) in San Antonio and from there joined the 654th Engineer Topographic Battalion at Camp McCoy, Wisconsin. He was put in Company B (Art, Drafting and Printing).
In December, 1943 the 654th was sent to Camp Shanks on the outskirts of New York City for a short while, and then crossed the Atlantic Ocean on the HMS Aquitania to Gourock, the port for Glasgow, Scotland. After a week in Glasgow, Dick Hedges was sent to Tetbury, England in the Cotswold Hills.
With the First U. S. Army headquarters in Bristol, England requested that its G-2 (air) form a new unit to be known as APID (Army or Aerial Photo Interpretation Detachment), Dick Hedges was assigned to it. He was put on P.I. team #15 and put in charge of APID's small drafting section. He was given a Top Secret BIGOT card and was sent to London to do special detailed work on beach maps for the invasion of Normandy. APID was living in tents in the woods at Middle Wallop near the Stonehenge in Southern England when the invasion of Normandy occurred on June 6, 1944.
Landing on Omaha beach at D+24, APID was at Airstrip #9 at Le Molay when Generals Eisenhower, Bradley and Montgomery visited in July at the time of the St. Lo breakthru.
APID moved from Normandy to Gif-sur-Yvette, a village south of Versailles, where the soldiers again lived in tents, but did their work in a huge chateau nearby.
In September APID then moved from France north to Gosselies, a suburb of the city of Charleroi, in southern Belgium.
For recreation, the 67th's three squadrons plus the attached groups such as APID, formed a basketball league and Dick Hedges coached and played on APID's team.
In March, 1945 APID left Belgium and moved east into Germany. The first stop was Ordensberg Vogelsang (Orderly Mountain Bird Chant) a former school for Hitler Jugend (Youth). From there they crossed the Rhine River at Remagen, and proceeded to Limburg, Germany.
When the war in Europe ended in May of 1945, APID was at Eschwege, Germany. After APID was disbanded, Dick Hedges was sent to Weisbaden, Germany where 12th Army Group Headquarters was located. Its code name was "Eagle." Dick Hedges applied for a job and was assigned to G-2. He was billeted with MFIU- 4 (Mobile Field Interrogation Unit #4) which operated the Weisbaden jail housing several high ranking Nazis.
In July 1945 Dick was sent to (Military Intelligence Service Center) at Oberursel, 12 miles from Frankfurt. He was promoted to Master Sergeant and put in charge of the library. While serving with MISC, Dick Hedges and Major Bill Silliman escorted five high ranking Nazis to Nurnberg to stand trial as war criminals. They were Field Marshall Albert Kesselring, commander of the Wermacht in North Africa, Italy and the Western Front; General of the Artillery Walter Warlimont; Reich Finance Minister Horace Greeley Hjalmar Schacht; Dr. William (Wilhelm) Stuckart, Secretary of the Minister of the Interior; and Frans Xavier Schwarz, the Treasurer of the NAZI party.
Several other excursions were taken out of "Dulag Luft" at Oberursel by groups of GIs who were stationed there. One was to the Buchenwald Concentration Camp near Weimar, Germany. Another was to Bavaria and Salzburg, Austria. While visiting in Austria, the group visited Hitler's former mountain top headquarters, "Adlerhorst" (Eagle's nest).
Dick Hedges spent three years in the United States Army earning the ranks of Private, T-5 (Corporal) for one year, T-4 (Sergeant), and T-3 (Staff Sergeant) for one year, Technical Sergeant and finally, Master Sergeant.
Among the many awards that he won were the Legion of Merit-Legionaire, Bronze Star, Good Conduct Medal and Victory Medal, American Theater of Operations medal, and the European Theater of Operations medal with five battle stars.
He received an Honorable Discharge from the United States Army at Camp McCoy, Wisconsin in March of 1946. After a shortvisit with his family in Iowa, he returned to Houston and his job in the Land Drafting Division of the Land Department of Shell Oil Company.
Scope and Contents
The Dick Hedges World War II Collection consisting of approximately 3.75 linear ft. of books, magazines, newspapers, clippings, photographs, photograph albums, maps, town plans, reports, writings and memorabilia, were collected by Dick Hedges while he was serving with the U. S. Army in Europe in World War II.
The various intelligence reports that are part of the collection were all extra copies and were declassified at the end of World War II.
The photograph albums containing pictures of Lt. Col. Otto Skorzeny and his friends were used by U. S. interrogators at the end of World War II.
Some of the German books in the collection, such as "Hitler wie ihn keiner kennt," "Deutschland Erwacht," "SS Kavallerie im Osten," and "Die Malerei der Gotik und Fruh Renaissance," can possibly be found in libraries in Germany.
Access Restrictions
Access to the x-rays of Adolph Hitler's head is restricted and requires permission from the Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, Rice University. All other material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift from Dixon D. (Dick) Hedges to Rice University in 1987.
Index Terms
Subjects
Soldiers -- Correspondence; World War (1939-1945); Politics and government
Document Types
postcards; clippings (information artifacts); Maps; photographs; corrrespondence; diaries
Subjects (Persons)
Hedges, Dixon D. (Dick)
- Series I: Personal, 217253
  Scope and Contents note
  One of the most interesting parts of the Personal series are the writings by Dick Hedges, of his many trips through Europe at the end of World War II, both personal and as a member of Military Intelligence Service Center. Of particular interest is "The Trip to Nurnberg," which chronicles his experiences while guarding various high ranking Nazi officials and generals to Nurnberg to stand trial as war criminals.
  This series also contains correspondence sent to and received by Dick Hedges while he was serving his tour of duty with the U.S. Army. Memorabilia from his army days can also be found in this series.
  - A Trip to Salzburg (With Photos, Newsclippings, Maps and Memorabilia), 217271 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Trip to Brussels (With Map), 217270 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Trip to Nurnburg (Including Cards, Photos, Newsclippings, Illustrations and Memorabilia), 217269 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Pecten, Volume 7, Nos. 7-8 (Shell Oil Co.), July - August 1945; 217268 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Military Engineer, October 1946; 217267 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Note of Explanation About Lt. Col. Otto Skorzeny, 217266 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interrogation of Julius Streicher, 217265 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family Correspondence, June 1942 - December 1944, n.d.; 217264 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, July 1944 - January 1946; 217263 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diary of Dick Hedges, 1942 - 1943; 217262 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Promotions, emblems, recommendations and application papers of Dick Hedges, 217261 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Drawings by Dick Hedges (See Series II, Skorzeny Report and Series IV, Publications (Apidigest) for additional drawings), 217260 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorabilia: address book, programs, cartoons, cards, drawing and tickets, 217259 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Longest Day (Magazine) - Darryl F. Zanuck, June 6, 1944; 217258 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Christmas and Birthday Greetings, 217257 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Guidebooks to Heidelberg and Salzberg, Dos and Don'ts in Brussels, 217256 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Turnover (Log) Book, December 15, 1944 - February 6, 1945; 217255 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorabilia - miscellaneous, 217254 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: German Leaders, 217242
  The material covers a period from approximately 1944 - 1946.
  Book titles in German have been written in both German and English on the guide for clarification.
  - Hitler wie ihn keiner kennt (Hitler as he is little known), Heinrich Hoffman, 217252 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Mind of Adolf Hitler. Walter C. Langer, 1972; 217251 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Excerpts by Dick Hedges from The End of Adolf Hitler, by Hanna Reitsch, February 11, 1946; 217250 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hitler as seen by his doctors, 217249 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1945 - 1987; 217248 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Skorzeny Report, July 23, 1945; 217247 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Most Dangerous Man in Europe": True, The Man's Magazine, January, 1948; 217246 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photograph Album: Colonel Otto Skorzeny, 217245 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Nurnberg Diary: Major B. D. Silliman, 217244 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - X-rays of Adolf Hitler's head (Restricted), 217243 (Box 2b, Folder 1)
- Series III: Intelligence, 217228
  This series consists of some very interesting interrogation reports about some of Germany's most notorious war criminals. "Economics: a German View" gives an excellent over-all picture of German thought concerning their own economic situation at the end of World War II, their hopes and fears for the future. Another interesting feature to be found in this series are the German Propoganda documents.
  - Interrogation, Friedrich von Boetticher, 217241 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Interrogation, Friedrich Fischer, 217240 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Interrogation, Field Marshall Karl von Runstedt's Summary of Operations in Europe, 217239 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Interrogation, Dr. Karl Ritter and Dr. Otto Meissner, 217238 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Political Situation in Belgium, January 29, 1946; 217237 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Types of German Obstacles (Beach Defenses at Normandy), Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force- Theatre Intelligence Section, 217236 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Intelligence Administration, 217235 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Report by The Supreme Commander to the Combined Chiefs of Staff of the Operations in Europe of the Allied Expeditionary Force, June 6, 1944 - May 8, 1945, 217234 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photo Interpretation Reports, November 1944; 217233 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Breakthrough in Western Germany, March 1945; 217232 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - U. S. Intelligence, Economics a German View, January 11, 1946; 217231 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - War Department Field Manual (FM 30-5) Military Intelligence, Combat Intelligence, February 1946; 217230 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Propaganda - Germany, 217229 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Publications, 217209
  The publication series has an excellent collections of newspaper clippings, books and magazines. The newspaper clippings includes copies of Stars and Stripes, and Apidigest, both military publications.
  - Stars and Stripes clippings, 217227 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 217226 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The API Digest, August 7, 1944-March 12, 1945; 217225 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The API Sentinel, November 20, 1944; 217224 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Recflash, 217223 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Der Stehgurt, July 1-Spetember 31, 1944; 217222 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yankee Kriegies, by Colonel C. Ross Greening and Sergeant Angello M. Spinelli, 217221 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bristol, Siren Nights: Diaries of the Blitzes, compiled by Rev. S. Paul Shipley, 217220 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - APID, 12th Army Group, 217219 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bivouac - 654th Engineer Topographic Battalion, 217218 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Souvenir aerial photos, 217217 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 30th Photo Reconnaissance Squadron, 67th Tactical Reconnaissance, Group, 9th Air Force, 217216 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 654th Engineer Topographic Battalion, 217215 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Report of Technical Operations, 654th Engineer Topographic Battalion, August 1, 1944-December 31, 1944; 217214 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Report of Technical Operations, 654th Engineer Topographic Battalion, December 21, 1943-June 30, 1944, July 4, 1944-August 1, 1944; 217213 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Report of Technical Operations, 654th Engineer Topographic Battalion, January 1, 1945-May 9, 1945; 217212 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Up Front, by Bill Mauldin, 217211 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Achtung Jabos!: The Story of the IX Tactical Air Command, 217210 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series V: Photographs and Postcards, 217194
  The material in this series consists of military and nonmilitary photographs. Some of the most interesting photos were taken while Dick Hedges visited Paris and other parts of Europe at the end of the war. Most of the photos of the Cherbourg, Omaha, and Utah beaches were taken just before the Normandy invasion in 1944.
  See Series I, II, III, and VIII for additional photographs.
  - Basketball Banquet, 1944-1945; 217208 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - King Leopold III of Belgium postcard, 217207 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Brussels, Versiers, Gosselies - Belgium, 217206 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pinup Girls of Nazi Luftwaffe Officers, 217205 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Personnel of the 1st U.S. Army Photo Interpretation Detachment - Gosselies, Beligium, March 5, 1945; 217204 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mont St. Michel, France, 217203 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Paris, France, 217202 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Oxford, England, 217201 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General Runstedt, 217200 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Germany (aerial views), 217199 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Bonn, Germany, 217198 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Beaches of Normandy (See Box 7 for Map), 217197 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Army Buddies", 217196 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Postcards (Belgium), 217195 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Topography, 217177
  The Topography series contains Maps, Town Plans, Guidebooks, and a War Department Technical Manual.
  Of special interest are the maps and townplans of Germany and England.
  See Series VII: Oversize for the map of Utah Beach.
  - Map and Aerial Photo Reading, Simplified, by Col. W. F. Heavey - Corps of Engineers, U.S. Army, 1942; 217193 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - War Department - Technical Manual, Topography and Surveying Map Reproduction, April 1942; 217192 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Map of Bristol, Bath and Cardiff - England, 217191 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Maps of London, 217190 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Map of England and Wales, 217189 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Maps of Brussels, 217188 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Map of Belgium, 217187 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Road Map to Germany, 217186 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Map of Europe - Grand Operations, 217185 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - War Department - Corps of Engineers, U.S. Army - Uncontrolled Mosaic (2nd edition) Defense Legend (map), 217184 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Map of Camp McCoy, Wisconsin, 217183 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Geographia" Pictorial Plan of London, 217182 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Belgium - Town Plans, 217181 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Holland Town - Plans, 217180 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Germany - Town Plans No. 1, 217179 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Germany - Town Plans No. 2, 217178 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Series VII: Oversize, 217164
  The material in this series is comprised of a mixture of Books, Photograph Albums, Newspapers, Magazines and a Map of Utah Beach for the Normandy invasion.
  One of the most exciting books in the collection is The Artists of the Gothic and Early Renaissance, which contains excellent color reproductions of famous paintings by Dutch, French, Italian and German artists. The book is catalogued separately and the call number is ND140 .W5 1938.
  Information on the battle of Iwo Jima, the Normandy Invasion and the death of Adolf Hitler can be found in the Stars and Stripes, a military newspaper.
  Of particular interest is the photograph album containing pictures of Colonel Otto Skorzeny training with the S.S. at an Summer Training Camp in Loas, Tyrol.
  - Map, Utah Beach - North (Ravenoville), April 21, 1944; 217176 (Box 7)
  - Stars and Stripes, The Daily Newspaper of the U.S. Armed Forces - Vol. 4, No. 188, June 10, 1944; 217175 (Box 7)
  - Stars and Stripes, The Daily Newspaper of the U.S. Armed Forces - Vol. 1, No. 32, February 20, 1945; 217174 (Box 7)
  - Stars and Stripes, The Daily Newspaper of the U.S. Armed Forces - Vol. 1, No. 28, May 2, 1945; 217173 (Box 7)
  - Deutschland erwacht - Werden, Kampf und Sieg (Germany Awakes - Will, Struggle and Victory) - Nazi Propagation Office, 1933; 217172 (Box 7)
  - Kavallerie Im Osten (Cavalry in the East), 1939-1942; 217171 (Box 7)
  - Der Adler, February 9, 1943; 217170 (Box 8)
  - Der Adler, May 1, 1943; 217169
  - Der Adler, June 1, 1943; 217168 (Box 8)
  - Der Weg Zur Ordensburg (The Way of the Orderly Town), 217167 (Box 8)
  - Die Malerei Der Gotik und Fruh Renaissance (The Artists of the Gothic and Early Renaissance), 217166 (Box 8)
    Separated Materials
    Catalogued separately. Call number ND140 .W5 1938
  - Skorzeny - Summer Training Camp Alpine Inn, Loas, Tyrol (Photograph Album), 217165 (Box 8)